<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arch-confraternity of the holy Rosary of our Blessed Lady</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838597</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arch-confraternity of the holy Rosary of our Blessed Lady</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22, 21-26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English Secret Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXVI. [1636]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>A description with indulgences, prayers, etc.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosary --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confraternities --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2981:1"/>
            <p>THE ARCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONFRATERNITY of the holy ROSARY of our Bleſſed Lady</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>publisher's device consisting of a Christogram with a cross and heart pierced by three nails</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>M.DC.XXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2981:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2981:2"/>
            <head>THE ARCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONFRATERNITY of the holy Roſary of our Bleſſed Lady.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Origin of the holy Roſary</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His holy Company was begun by S. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick, founder of the renowned Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious order of the Friar Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, about the year 1216. to extirpate the Hereſie of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſes, as it did; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, brought ſuch fruit to the Church of God, that Popes, the more to recommend and make it famous, have endowed it with many priviledges and indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as you ſhall here ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At their firſt entrance or admittance.</head>
               <p>Entring into this noble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternity,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2981:3"/>they gaine a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Indulgence, granted by the Popes, Pius V. &amp; Clement VIII.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Sundayes of the month.</head>
               <p>Every firſt Sunday of the Month, (principally of October-having confeſſed &amp; communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, thy gain a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Alſo viſiting the Church or being preſent at the Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Roſary, a plenary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. Greg. XIII Paul V.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſeaven feaſts of our Lady.</head>
               <p>On the Purification, Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, Viſitation, Aſſumption, Nativity, Preſentation, and Conception of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, being confeſſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, or having a will to do it in due time, a plenary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. Alſo, viſiting the Church, or being preſent at the Proceſſions of the Roſary, a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2981:3"/>plenary indulgence. Pius IV.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To every Myſtery of the holy Roſary.</head>
               <p>They are fifteen, devided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts. Five, are c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lled joyful, whereon they are to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate in ſaying the firſt Chapler (or Beads of five Decads of our Lady, the Annunciation, Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of S. Elizabeth, Nativity of our Saviour, his Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Finding of him in the Temple; Five, called dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, in ſaying the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, the ſweat of Bloud, Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at the pillar, crowning with thornes, larrying of his Croſſe and Crucifixion; and, Five glorious, in ſaying the third Chaplet, the Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, coming of the Holy Ghoſt, Aſſumption of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lady, and her Coronation: Upon all, and every the feaſts of which Myſteries, as alſo on the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2981:4"/>celebrity of the crown of our Saviour, the Invention and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of the holy Croſſe, and the day of all Saints, viſiting the Alter of the Roſary, may be gained, a plenary Indulgence. Greg. 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Maſſe of the holy Roſary.</head>
               <p>Every time that one ſayeth it, cauſeth it to be ſayd, or is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it, a plenary Indulgence. Alex. VI. Paul. III.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For ſaying and carrying the Roſary about one.</head>
               <p>Saying the whole Roſary, they gain three hundred ſixty thouſand and fifteen yeares, five quarantaines, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fourty dayes pardon. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noc. 8. Alex. 8. Clem. 5. Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. 6. Sixt. 4. Clem. 8. Alex. and Raimond Legats. And,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2981:4"/>which is more, a plenary indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Paul. 3.</p>
               <p>Carrying publikely, and for to give good example, the Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Chaplet bleſſed by a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican Friar, they gain every day two hundred quarantaines of indulgence. Inno. 8. Alex. 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Indulgences of the Stations of Rome, which every day are ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, in one part or other of the Citty, with delivery alſo of ſoules out of Purgatory.</head>
               <p>THey are gained by viſiting five Altars, and ſaying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one of them five Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſters, and five Ave Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, or elſe, five and twenty Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Ave, before one only Altar, if there be no more. Paul 3. Clement 8. Yea, it ſuffiſeth to ſay only five Paters and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, but before an Altar of the Roſary. Pius. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2981:5"/>
               <head>At the diſcretion of the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Confraternity.</head>
               <p>Twice in their life, on the dayes they pleaſe to make choice of, being confeſſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, they may gain a plenary indulgence. Innoc. 8. Clement 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Salve Regina.</head>
               <p>Hearing the Salve Regina after Complet in the Churches of S. Dominick, a hundred yeares and fourty dayes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. Paul. 5. Alex. Legat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Doing of good workes.</head>
               <p>Every time they viſit the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of the holy Roſary, or goe to ſee the ſick exhorting them to receive the Sacraments, a hundred and ſixty dayes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. Greg. 13. Clement 8.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2981:5"/>
               <p> Being preſent at the divine Offices, publike or private aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Roſary, making peace between thoſe who are at diſcord, and, whatſoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good work, ſixty dayes of pardon. Clement 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For thoſe who are ſick or hindred.</head>
               <p>The ſick, or ſuch as for other lawful impediments, cannot be preſent at the meeting of the Confraternity, communicating, and ſaying the Roſary, or ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Pſalmes, before ſome devout picture, gain all the ſame indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, which they get who are aſſiſtant. Pius 5. Greg. 13. Sixt. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At the hour of death.</head>
               <p>At the hour of death, being confeſſed and communicated, a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2981:6"/>plenary Indulgence. Having the bleſſed candle of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternity, a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. Saying with mouth or heart JESUS MARIA, a plenary Indulgence; and, ſuch an abſolution as one is thereby reſtored, to the purity and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency which he had by ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme. Innoc. 8. Adrian 6. Greg. 13. Pius 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the Dead.</head>
               <p>Accompaning the Dead to their buriall, a hundred ſixty dayes of Indulgence. Greg. 13. Clement 8. Being preſent at the Maſſes and Offices of the Dead, they gain five thouſand four hundred yeares, and a hundred and fourty dayes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Sixt. 4. Alex. 6. Greg. 13. Clem. 8, Every time they ſay the whole Roſary, they gain
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2981:6"/>the delivery of a ſoul out of Purgatory. Paul 3. Whoſoever of the forenamed on fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſayeth, cauſeth to be ſaid, or is preſent when one ſaith Maſſe of the Roſary, to that intention, delivereth a ſoul out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. Paul 5. All the pardons granted to the living, may be applyed to the Dead, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating, ſaying the Roſary, Maſſe, or making the ſtations for them. Leo 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For all Faithful people.</head>
               <p>At the ſound of the Ave Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria at night, ſaying:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Angelus Domini nunciavit Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae, &amp; concepit de Spiritu Sancto: Ave Maria. Ecce ancilla Domini: fiat mihi ſecundum verbum tuum, Ave Maria. Et verbum caro fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt, &amp; habitavit in nobis: Deo gratias, Ave Maria;</hi> They
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2981:7"/>gain a plenary Indulgence. Paul 3. When the hour ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, by ſaying an <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> a thouſand dayes pardon. Leo 10. Saying the Office of our bleſſed Lady, at every Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall hour, they gain fourty dayes of Indulgence. John. 22. and other fifty granted by Pius 5. Invoking the holy names of JESUS and MARIA, ninety five dayes of pardon. Urban. 4. John 22. Pius 5. Bending reverently at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or pronouncing of the ſaid holy names of JESUS and MARIA, two hundred yeares, In the <hi>Ave maria,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Jeſus</hi> adding <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes pardon, ſaying withall the reſt of the ſame, <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> and the <hi>Salve Regina.</hi> As alſo ſtanding up at <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat,</hi> fourty dayes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2981:7"/>John 22. Reciting the prayer <hi>Ave Sanctiſſima Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> eleven thouſand yeares of Indulgences, granted by Sixtus 4. Saying: Bleſſed and praiſed be the moſt holy Virgin Marie, a hundred yeares of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Paul 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Triviledges of the Confraters.</head>
               <p>THey are as Religious of the holy Order S. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick, and (beſides their own) are partakers of all the good works of that renowned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the whole world through both before and after Death. A rare priviledge. Innoc. 8. At Eaſter, Nativity, Annunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Viſitation, Purification, and Aſſumption of our Lady, and three dayes before, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican Fathers may abſolve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2981:8"/>them from all caſes reſerved, even to the Pope, (ſo they be not comprehended <hi>In Bulla Coenae</hi>) and releaſe them of all oathes, and change their vowes, except the five ordinary. Leo 10. Being Dead, they have at leaſt four Maſſes a year ſaid for them in the Convents of S. Dominick, and places where there is a Confraternity; And who ſhall be there preſent the dayes after the Purification, Annunciation, Aſſumption, and Nativity of our Lady, ſhall gain a thouſand nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred dayes of pardon. Granted by nineteen Cardinals of the ſaid Confraternity, in the year 1479.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2981:8"/>
               <head>Conditions requiſite for Admittance.</head>
               <p>They muſt make their names be writ in a book kept for that end, confeſſe and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and ſay at leaſt a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let or pair of Beads of five de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cads. Pius 5. If one ſhould cauſe Children to be admitted, of ſuch as were abſent, or dead, (a thing very frequent) he were not at all obliged, either for them, or for himſelf, under pain of ſin, nor bound to pay ought, without he freely of h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> own accord ſhould pleaſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it. They are to ſay three pair of Beads the week of five Decads, or their Chaplet, at one or more times. Paul 3. And that in ſuch a place, and poſture of body, as they themſelves pleaſe, and when they omit to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2981:9"/>ſay them, though there be no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet gain they not the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons for that time. Yet, in caſe, they have ſaid, or ſhall ſay them double, (that is, twice ſo many Chaplets, or Beades of five Decads,) the week be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or after, or ſhould cauſe any other of the Confraternity to ſay them for them, they ſhould not looſe the pardons. An eaſy matter to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All the aforeſaid matters are gathered out of authentick bookes and buls confirmed by Paulus V.</hi> 1608. <hi>bulla cumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim foelic. record.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2981:9"/>
               <head>A prayer againſt the plague taken out of the chronicle of the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical order of the fryers Minors written by the Reverend Father Francis Genzaga of the ſame Order.</head>
               <p>THe whole City of Conimbris, being viſited with a moſt grievous plague this place alſo (that is to ſay the Monaſtery of thoſe ſiſters of S. Clare who are termed the urbaniſt nuns) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be infected; and whilſt the Abbeſſe ſtood very ſolicitous at the grace. for the diſpoſall of the ſiſters ſubjected un to her, to ſome place, for the ſafety of their lives; then ſuddenly appeared a begger, demanding the cauſe of her ſo great ſorrow and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude? and being thereof cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, he delivered, her a ſmall ſcroul of parchment, ſaying, If you will cauſe, the Anthemne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2981:10"/>and the prayer contained in that ſmall ſcroul, to be often and daily repeated; this place ſhall not be touched with any plague at all, and having thus ſpoken, he vaniſhed away; the nuns took this begger to be S. Bartholomew; but whoſoever that was; without all doubt it is; that the monaſtery from that time, ſtood free from any peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous contagion; when the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conimbris it ſelf ſtood infected.</p>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
                  <head>The Prayer.</head>
                  <p>STella Coeli extirpavit, quae lactavit Dominum, mortis peſtem quam plantavit primus parens hominum. Ipſa ſtella nunc dignetur ſydera compeſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quorum bella plebem cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt dirae mortis ulcere, O pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſima ſtella Maris, a peſte ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2981:10"/>nobis. Audi nos domina; nam filius tuus nihil negans te honorat. Salva nos Jeſu, pro quibus virgo mater te orat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Verſ.</label> Ora pro nobis ſancta Dei genitrix.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reſp.</label> Ut digni efficiamur pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſonibus Chriſti.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Oremus.</label> DEus miſericordiae, Deus pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis, Deus indulgentiae, qui miſertus es ſuper afflictionem populi tui, &amp; dixiſti Angelo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutienti populum tuum; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne manum tuam: ob amorem illius ſtellae glorioſae, cujusube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pretioſa contra venenum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum, delictorum quam dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer ſuxiſti, praeſta auxilium gratiae tuae: Et ab omnipeſte &amp; improviſa morte ſecure libere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, &amp; a totius perditionis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſu miſericorditer ſalvemur.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2981:11"/>Per te Jeſu Chriſte Rex gloriae, qui vivis &amp; regnas in ſaecula ſaeculorum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reſp.</label> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <p>The ſtarr of heaven (that gave ſuck to our Lord) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirped the plague of death, which the firſt parent of men planted; let that ſtarr now be pleaſed to appeaſe the skyes, whoſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature, Killeth the people with an ulcer of dreadfull death.</p>
                  <p>O moſt holy ſtarre of the ſea preſerve us from the plague, hear us OB. Lady, for thy ſon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying thee not any thing, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth thee, ſave us O Jeſu for whom the Virgin Mother pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Verſ.</label> Pray for us O holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reſp.</label> That we may be made wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy of the promiſes of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2981:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Let us Pray.</label> O God of mercy, God of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, God of pardon, which haſt mercy upon the affliction of thy people, and ſaid to the Angel wounding the people, hold thy hand, even for the love of that glorious ſtarr, whoſe pretious breſts, againſt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime of our ſins, thou didſt moſt ſweetly ſuck, vouchſafe us, the help of thy grace, that we may be ſafely delivered, from all plague &amp; unprovided death, and that we may be mercifully ſaved from the aſſault of all perdition; through thee JESUS CHRIST, King of Glory, who liveſt and Reigneſt world without end. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A Prayer to S. Francis.</head>
                  <p>HAyl O holy Father S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, the light of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the forme of the minors,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2981:12"/>the mirour of vertues, the way of right, the rule of manners; bring us from the exile of fleſh, to the Kingdome of heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Verſ.</label> Pray for us holy S. Francis.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reſp.</label> That we may be made worthy of the promiſes of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Let us Pray.</label> O God which doſt by the merits of S. Francis enlarge thy Church, with the fruit of a new iſſue, grant us, by his imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to deſpiſe worldly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and continually to enjoy the participation of heavenly guifts: through Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="litany">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2981:12"/>
                  <head>LITANIES of our B. Lady.</head>
                  <list type="litany">
                     <item>Kyrie eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Lord have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Kyrie eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Lord have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte audi nos.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt hear us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt graciouſly hear us.</item>
                     <item>Pater de coelis Deus. Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>God the Father of Heaven, have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Fili Redemptor mundi Deus miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>God the Son Redeemer of the world have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2981:13"/>
                     <item> Spiritus ſancte Deus miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>God the holy Ghoſt have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Sancta Trinitas unus Deus Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>Holy Trinity one God, have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Sancta Maria, ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>Holy Mary, pray for us.</item>
                     <item>Sancta Dei Genitrix ora.</item>
                     <item>Holy Mother of God, pray.</item>
                     <item>Sancta Virgo Virginum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Holy Virgin of Virgins, pray. for us.</item>
                     <item>Mater Chriſti, ora.</item>
                     <item>Mother of Chriſt, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater Divinae gratiae, ora.</item>
                     <item>Mother of Divine grace, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater puriſſima, ora.</item>
                     <item>Moſt pure Mother, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater Caſtiſſima, ora.</item>
                     <item>Moſt chaſt Mother, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater inviolata, ora.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2981:13"/>
                     <item> Undefiled Mother, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater intemerata, ora.</item>
                     <item>Untouched Mother, pray,</item>
                     <item>Mater Amabilis, ora.</item>
                     <item>Amiable Mother, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater Admirabilis, ora.</item>
                     <item>Admirable Mother, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater Creatoris, ora.</item>
                     <item>Mother of our Creatour, pray.</item>
                     <item>Mater Salvatoris, ora.</item>
                     <item>Mother of our Saviour, pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo prudentiſſima, ora.</item>
                     <item>Moſt prudent Virgin, pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo veneranda, ora.</item>
                     <item>Venerable Virgin, pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo praedicanda, ora.</item>
                     <item>Renowned Virgin pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo potens, ora.</item>
                     <item>Potent Virgin, pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo clemens, ora.</item>
                     <item>Clement Virgin, pray.</item>
                     <item>Virgo fidelis, ora.</item>
                     <item>Faithfull Virgin, pray.</item>
                     <item>Speculum juſtitiae, ora.</item>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2981:14"/>
                     <item> Mirour of Juſtice, pray.</item>
                     <item>Sedes ſapientiae, ora.</item>
                     <item>Seat of Wiſdome, pray.</item>
                     <item>Cauſa noſtrae laetitiae, ora.</item>
                     <item>Cauſe of our gladneſſe, pray.</item>
                     <item>Vas Spirituale, ora.</item>
                     <item>Spirituall veſſell, pray.</item>
                     <item>Vas inſigne devotionis, ora.</item>
                     <item>Veſſell of Singular devotion, pray.</item>
                     <item>Roſa Miſtica, ora.</item>
                     <item>Miſticall Roſe, pray.</item>
                     <item>Turris Davidica, ora.</item>
                     <item>Towre of David, pray.</item>
                     <item>Turris Eburnea, ora.</item>
                     <item>Towre of Ivory, pray.</item>
                     <item>Domus Aurea, ora.</item>
                     <item>Houſe of Gold, pray.</item>
                     <item>Foederis Arca, ora.</item>
                     <item>Ark of the Covenant, pray.</item>
                     <item>Janua Coeli, ora.</item>
                     <item>Gate of Heaven, pray.</item>
                     <item>Stella Matutina, ora.</item>
                     <item>Morning ſtarr, pray.</item>
                     <item>Salus infirmorum, ora.</item>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2981:14"/>
                     <item> Health of the weak, pray.</item>
                     <item>Refugium peccatorum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Refuge of Sinners, pray.</item>
                     <item>Conſolatrix Afflictorum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Comfort of the afflicted, pray. for us.</item>
                     <item>Auxilium Chriſtianorum, ora. pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>Help of Chriſtians, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Angelorum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Angels, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Patriarcharum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Patriarchs, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Prophetarum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Prophets, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Apoſtolorum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Apoſtles, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Martyrum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Martyrs, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Confeſſorum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Confeſſours, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Virginum, ora.</item>
                     <item>Queen of Virgins, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Sanctorum omnium ora pro nobis.</item>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2981:15"/>
                     <item> Queen of all Saints, pray.</item>
                     <item>Regina Sanctiſſimi Roſarii, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pro nobis.</item>
                     <item>Queen of the moſt Bleſſed Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, pray.</item>
                     <item>Agnus Dei, qui tollis peccata mundi, Parce nobis Domine.</item>
                     <item>Lamb of God, who taketh away the ſins of the world, Spare us O Lord,</item>
                     <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Exaudi nos Domine Lamb of God who taketh away the ſins af the world, Hear us O Lord.</item>
                     <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                     <item>Lamb of God who taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of the world, Have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte audi nos.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt hear us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt gratiouſly hear us.</item>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2981:15"/>
                     <item> Kyrie eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Lord have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Chriſte eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Chriſt have mercy upon us.</item>
                     <item>Kyrie eleiſon.</item>
                     <item>Lord have mercy upon us.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>WEe fly unto thy protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on O holy Mother of God, deſpiſe not our prayers in our neceſſities, but deliver us continually from all dangers; O glorious and Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Verſ.</label> Pray for us O holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Reſp.</label> That we may be made worthy of the promiſes of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2981:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Let us pray.</label> O God who under the miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Roſary of the Mother of God, doſt repreſent unto us all the miſteries of thy life, death and glory; grant that whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we do get to be of this plantation, may be crowned with a triumphant garland of the heavenly Garden; who liveſt and reigneſt for ever and ever Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2981:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
